Finding Aid for the Otto Kinkeldey Papers, 1898-1962
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Otto Kinkeldey Papers, 1898-1962
Mus. Arc. 54
Kinkeldey, Otto, 1878-1966
4 boxes ( 147 folders )
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains offprints of articles by Otto Kinkeldey and others, correspondence, documents related to the Committee on Graduate Study in Music (1938), Kinkeldey's transcriptions of musical works, and one of his own compositions.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Otto Kinkeldey (1878-1966) was among the most prominent and influential of the first generation of musicologists and music librarians in the United States. He earned his Master of the Arts degree in English literature and philosophy at New York University in 1900. After continuing studying music with Edward MacDowell at Columbia University for two years Kinkeldey moved to Germany to study at the Akademie Institut für Kirchenmusik and at the University of Berlin where his musicology professors included Johannes Wolf, Oskar Fleischer, Max Friedländer, and Hermann Kretzschmar. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Berlin in 1909.
In addition to receiving his musicological training in Germany, Kinkeldey also gained experience as a librarian while working as a cataloger for the Prussian government. His work involved cataloging music collections in church and town libraries. He was hired in 1909 to be the librarian for the Royal Academic Institute for Church Music in Breslau where he also worked at the University of Breslau as professor of organ and music theory. He taught with such distinction that the Prussian government granted him the honorary title, "Royal Prussian Professor" in 1910.
Kinkeldey returned to the United States in 1914 and was named chief of the Music Division of the New York Public Library in 1915. His work was interrupted while he was enlisted in the United States Army in 1917-1919. Kinkeldey resigned his post at the New York Public Library in 1923. He left to become head of the Music Department at Cornell University but returned to the New York Public Library for the years 1927-1930.
Cornell University created the first faculty position in musicology in 1930 and appointed Kinkeldey to the position. From 1930-1946 he also served as University Librarian at Cornell. After he retired from Cornell University he continued his career in several locations as a visiting faculty member, including Harvard, Princeton, Illinois University, Berkeley, and North Texas University.
Kinkeldey was one of the founding members of the American Musicological Society in 1941 and its first president. He was also among the founders of the Music Library Association in 1931 and served as its first president. He was instrumental in establishing the standards for graduate programs in music in the United States. His research and writings encompass both musicological and bibliographical studies.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains twenty-one of Kinkeldey's published writings (two of which are only abstracts of presentations), documents from the 1936 meeting of the Committee on Graduate Study in Music chaired by Howard Hanson that established guidelines for music graduate programs, correspondence concerning a publication of the hymnal, Zion's Harfe and seventeen writings by other authors, some with inscriptions to Kinkeldey or accompanied by correspondence to him. The collection also contains eleven items of assorted correspondence, four folders of program materials, and five folders of paleographic examples.
The musical portion of the collection reflects Kinkeldey's research interests. The transcriptions pre-date commercially available transcriptions made later by other musicologists. Many of the transcriptions were used in his doctoral dissertation Orgel und Klavier in der Musik des 16. Jahrhunderts. Some of the musical works in Series IX were separated from original placements within compilations in order to better identify the contents.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in nine series:
I. Writings by Kinkeldey
II. Committee on Graduate Study in Music
III. Correspondence about Zions Harfe
IV. Writings by others
V. Correspondence
VI. Programs
VII. Paleographic examples
VIII. Compositions by Kinkeldey
IX. Transcriptions by Kinkeldey
Container List
- Writings by Kinkeldey, 1909-1954, I.; Folder 1-24
  Arranged in two series:
  A. Published writings
  B. Unpublished writings
  - Published writings, 1909-1954, I.A; Folder 1-21
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Alfred Einstein's 'The Italian Madrigal': a review, 1949, 1 offprint (20 pages); Published in: Renaissance News, v. 2 n. 2 (Summer 1949): 25-28. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American higher music education compared with that of Europe, 1934, 1 offprint (16 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association, 29 (1934): 20-28. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Artist and the scholar, 1940, 1 offprint (15 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association, 35 (1940): 67-79. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bach embellecido por sí mismo, 1954, 1 offprint (10 pages); Published in: Revista de Estudios Musicales n. 7 (December 1954): 1-10. Translated by Francisco Curt Lange. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Changing relations within the field of musicology, 1936, 1 offprint (19 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association 31 (1936): 246-261. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Exhibition of music, 1930, 1 journal (68 pages); Published in: Bulletin of the New York Public Library v. 34 n. 1 (January 1930): 3-8. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Franchino Gafori and Marsilio Ficino, 1947, 1 offprint (4 pages); Published in: Harvard Library Bulletin v. 1 n. 1 (Autumn 1947): [379]-382. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Hopes and wishes, 1941, 1 offprint (8 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association 36 (1941): 190-197. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Influence of folk-music upon artistic progress, 1915, 1 offprint (13 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association 10 (1915): 272-284. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Jewish dancing master of the Renaissance (Guglielmo Ebreo), 1929, 1 illustrated leaf; Published in: Studies in Jewish Bibliography and Related Subjects, in Memory of Abraham Solomon Freidus (1867-1923): 329-372. Only the illustration of the dancing master is contained within, the full text of the article. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Music and meaning: abstract, 1936, 1 offprint (16 pages); Published in: Bulletin of the American Musicological Society n. 1 (June 1936): 14-15. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Music education and public libraries, 1916, 1 journal 15 (pages); Published in: Music Bulletin v. 3 n. 1 (September 1916): 11-14. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Music in the universities of Europe and North America, 1915, 1 offprint (12 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association 10: 79-90. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Music of the future: a phantasy: abstract, 1937, 1 journal (32 pages); Published in: Bulletin of the American Musicological Society n. 2 (June 1937): 4. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Musicology in American colleges and universities, 1934, 1 offprint (8 pages); Published in: Yearbook of the Music Educators National Conference 27: 125-131. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Musik in Schlesien, 1913, 1 offprint (9 pages); Published in: Schlesische Landeskunde Geschichtliche Abteilung (1913): 342-350. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Orgel und Klavier in der Musik des 16. Jahrhunderts: ein Beitrag zur Geschichte der Instrumentalmusik: Kapitel VII, Anhang I, II: Inaugural Dissertation zur Erlangung der Doktorwürde genehmigt von der philosophischen Fakultat der Friedrich-Wilhelms-Universität zu Berlin, 1909, 1 book (40 pages) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Preparation of the college music student for graduate study, 1934, 1 offprint (16 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association 29 (1934): 165-170. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Thomas Mace and his 'Musick's Monument' (1676), 1937, 1 journal (32 pages); Published in: Bulletin of the American Musicological Society n. 2 (June 1937): 21. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Thomas Robinson's 'Schoole of Musicke': a lute book of Shakespeare's time, 1936, 1 journal (16 pages); Published in: Bulletin of the American Musicological Society n. 1 (June 1936): 7. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Tributes to the memory of Oscar George Sonneck (1873-1928), 1928, 1 offprint (7 pages); Published in: Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association 23 (1928): 257-263. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Unpublished writings, 1919, 1923, undated, I.B; Folder 22-24
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Comments on Hans Tessmer's article Joh. Sebastian Bach im öffentlichen Schriftum seiner Zeit, published in the journal, Neue-Musik Zeitung, 1919, 1 manuscript leaf (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Labels for an untitled exhibit about Beethoven at the New York Public Library, 1923, 1 envelope; Presumably curated by Kinkeldey. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Notes on, and text of Alfred Tennyson's poem, Maud as set by Sir Arthur Somervell, undated, 2 folded manuscript leaves (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Committee on Graduate Study in Music, 1936-1937, II.; Folder 25-30
  Documents related to the Special Committee on Graduate Study in Music jointly sponsored by the Music Teachers National Association and the National Association of Schools of Music. The committee was first authorized in December 1933. The enclosed contents pertain to the committee's meeting December 30, 1936 at the joint conventions of the Music Teachers National Association, National Association of Schools of Music, American Musicological Society, and Phi Mu Alpha Fraternity in Chicago, Illinois and subsequent documents. The authors of the typescript documents are not stated.
  Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Constitution and by-laws, specimen examinations, approved curricula, code of ethics, membership of the National Association of Schools of Music, 1936, 1 printed booklet (35 pages) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Meeting of special committee, December 28, 1936, 32 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Transcription of meeting of the Committee on Graduate Study in Music chaired by Howard Hanson.
  - Adjourned meeting of special committee, December 30, 1936, 53 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Summary of meetings of Committee on Graduate Study in Chicago 1937, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Items of agreement and regulations for the Doctor of Philosophy in Music degree.
  - Letter from Hanson, Howard, 1896-1981 to Kinkeldey, 19 January 1937, 2 typescript leaves (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Letter sent with transcript of second meeting of the Committee on Graduate Study in Music.
  - Preliminary report of the Committee on Graduate Study in Music undated (1937?), 1 printed booklet (16 pages) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Annotated with changes.
- Correspondence about Zions Harfe, March 18, 1938-June 10, 1938, III.; Folder 31-34
  Correspondence related to Kinkeldey's English translations of hymns from the German edition of Zions Harfe, the primary worship hymnal of the Apostolic Christian Church.
  Arranged alphabetically by sending correspondent's surname.
  - Braun, G. A. to Kinkeldey, 18 March 1938-21 May 1938, 14 typescript letters (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Includes one item written on behalf of Braun by Albert J. Strohm. Letterhead on one item: "G. A. Braun, Inc., Exclusive Mid-Western distributors, The Prosperity Co., Inc.. Laundry and Dry Cleaning Equipment, 612 N. Michigan Avenue, Chicago".
  - Kinkeldey, Otto, 1858-1958 to G. A. Braun, 12 May 1938-10 June 1938, 5 typescript letters (5 leaves) and 29 manuscript and typescript leaves of translations (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Spencer, Charles W. to Kinkeldey, 8 June 1938, 1 typescript letter (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Spencer was librarian of Colgate University Library, Hamilton, New York. He wrote to respond that the choir at the school had not performed a specified hymn from Zions Harfe.
  - Stieg, Lewis to Kinkeldey, 4 June 1938, 1 typescript letter (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Stieg was a librarian at Hamilton College, Clinton, New York. He wrote to respond that the choir at the school had not performed a specified hymn from Zions Harfe.
- Writings by Others, 1905-1960, IV.; Folder 35-52
  Chiefly published writings by other authors, some accompanied by correspondence.
  Arranged alphabetically by author's surname and then by title.
  - Akademischen Vereins Organum, July 1898, 28 September 1905, 2 items (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Statut des akademischen Vereins Organum zu Berlin, Juli 1898. Printed pamphlet (8 pages)
    Organum, Bier-Zeitung, 28. Sept. 1905. Handwritten newsletter (13 pages).
  - Barbour, J. Murray (James Murray), 1897-1970: Irregular systems of temperament, 1947, 1 offprint (7 pages); Published in: Journal of the American Musicological Society, v. 1 n. 3 (Autumn 1948): 20-26 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Accompanied by two concert programs from Michigan State College Department of Music Collegium Musicum.
  - Barbour, J. Murray (James Murray), 1897-1970: Music and continued ternary fractions, 1948, 1 offprint (11 pages); Published in: American Mathematical Monthly, v. 55 n. 9 (November 1948): 545-555. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Barbour, J. Murray (James Murray), 1897-1970: Musical scales and their classification, 1949, 1 offprint (4 pages); Published in: Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, v. 21 n. 6 (November 1949): 586-589. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Besseler, Heinrich, 1900-1969: Johann Sebastian Bach 1685-1750, 1935, 1 offprint (26 pages); Published in: Die Grossen Deutschen: Neue deutsche Biographie: 94-111. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Cornell University: Honor Dr. Kinkeldey at sixtieth birthday, 24 November 1938, 1 printed booklet(16 pages); Published in: Cornell Alumni News, v. 41 n. 9 (November 24, 1938): 109. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Ellinwood, Leonard, 1905-1994: Francesco Landini and his music, 1936, 1 offprint (29 pages); Published in: Musical Quarterly, v. 22 n. 2 (April 1936): 190-216. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Accompanied by three manuscript transcriptions of Landini works: Amor in uon gentile, Partesi con dolore, and Si dolce non sono (2nd part). The score of the last work is an ozalid reproduction. There is also a copy of the last work as it appears in the Squarcialupi Codex.
  - Emmanuel, Maurice, 1862-1938: Rythme d'Euripide à Debussy, 1928, 1 printed article (16 pages); Published in: Le Monde Musicale, v. 38 n. 9 (September 1928): 277-329. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Annotated and accompanied by three manuscript items. One from Emmanuel to Maurice Brillant, October 11, 1930; two manuscript lists in unidentified hand concerning articles by or about Emmanuel in Revue Musicale
  - Guise, Cedric H. (Cedric Hay), b. 1890: Mr. Guise's collection of ragtime, 1951, 9 typescript leaves (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Haydon, Glen, 1896-1966: Lateran Codex 61, 1958, 1 offprint (6 pages); Published in: Bericht über den siebenten internationalen musikwissenschaftlichen Kongress Köln 1958: 126-131. (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Hornbostel, Erich Moritz von, 1877-1935: Psychologie der Gehörserscheinungen, 1926, 1 offprint (30 pages); Published in: Handbuch der normalen und pathologischen Physiologie v. 11, n. 1: 701-730. (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Johnson, Harold E. (Harold Edgar), 1915-1985: Sibeliuksen Lemminkäissarja, 1957, 1 offprint (5 pages); Published in: Ylipainos Helsingen Sanomista May 19 1957: 3-7. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Lach, Robert, 1874-1958: Schubert und das Volkslied, 1929, 1 offprint (9 pages); Published in: Bericht über den internationalen Kongress für Schubert-Forschung Wien 1928: 59-67. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Matzke, Hermann Karl Anton, 1890-1976: Von der Erziehung zur Musik, 1920, 1 booklet (32 pages); Breslau: Richard Hoppe, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Accompanied by manuscript letter from Matzke to Kinkeldey, 15 March 1922.
  - New York Public Library: Bibliography of works by and on C. P. E. Bach in the New York Public Library, circa 1932, 2 typescript leaves (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Schrade, Leo, 1903-1964: Ästhetik Albert Schweitzers: eine Interpretation Bachs, January 1960, 1 offprint (18 pages); Published in: Universitas: Zeitschrift für Wissenschaft, Kunst und Literatur 15. Jahrgang Heft 1 (January 1960): 61-78. (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Sleeper, Helen Joy: Preliminary draft of a check-list of thematic catalogues, prepared for the Music Library Association by the Committee on indexes (1942-1946), 1946, 22 typescript leaves; Written with co-authors Leonard Burkat and Scott Goldthwaite. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Accompanied by 1 typescript letter from Sleeper to Kinkeldey 18 March 1942 and 1 typescript addition, Brief description of the proposed format of the Check-list of thematic catalogues.
  - Sleeper, Helen Joy: String fantasias of John Jenkins, 14 August 1936, 11 typescript leaves; "Seminar report for Music S20". (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Correspondence, 1904-1960, V.; Folder 53-62
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent's surname, including one from Kinkeldey.
  - Bailey, Parker: 15 July 1934, 1 typescript leaf (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Calmus, Georgy: 13 January 1913, 1 manuscript leaf; In German. (Box 2, Folder 53a)
  - Ehrenzweig, Erica: 1 September 1943, 1 typescript leaf; In German. (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Written on behalf of musicologist Otto Erich Deutsch concerning a publication of Parthenia.
  - Hourlier, Jacques: 7 January 1960, 25 January 1960, and undated, 3 manuscript items (3 leaves); In English and French. The letters are addressed to "Monsieur le Professor". The undated letter bears an inscription suggesting that the addressee was Carl Parrish, not Kinkeldey. (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Joseffy, Carl: 25 January 1941, 1 typescript leaf; In English. (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Kinkeldey, Otto, 1878-1966: circa 1959, 2 manuscript leaves; In English. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Letter to Sydney Beck concerning the 1959 publication of the volume edited by Beck, Thomas Morley's First Book of Consort Lessons.
  - Schneider, Marius, 1903-1982: undated, 1 manuscript leaf; In German. (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Van Loan, Philip: circa 1924, 1 manuscript leaf; In English. (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Wolf, Johannes, 1869-1947: 1 March 1904, 1 manuscript leaf; In German. (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Unidentified: 31 March 1911, 1 manuscript leaf; In German. (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Unidentified: undated, 1 manuscript leaf; In French. (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Programs, 1911-1938, VI.; Folder 63-66
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Fourth Congress of the International Musical Society: 1911, 3 items (Box 2, Folder 63)
    3 May 1911, Reception by the Worshipful Company of Grocers, at Grocers' Hall, with program for events 29 May - 3 June
    2 June 1911 Banquet at Savoy Hotel program with alphabetical list of guests
    2 June 1911 Concert program for performance by The Band of the Royal Regiment of Artillery at the Savoy Hotel
  - Dô^me des Invalides (Paris, France): 9 June 1914, 1 program (4 pages); Can not confirm if item was associated with Kinkeldey or not. (Box 2, Folder 64)
    Concert de musique religieuse in the Chapelle des Invalides. with performers including organist Joseph Bonnet, conductor Felix Raugel, violoncellist Françoise Gervais, and violinist Eugène. Borrel.
  - Member's ticket for International Society for Musical Research, now known as the International Musicological Society Congress at Cambridge, England, 1933, 1 card (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Cornell University celebration in commemoration of Otto Kinkeldey's sixtieth birthday, 1938, 6 items (Box 2, Folder 66)
    Contains a musical canon, text to the Alma Mater for the Western New York Branch of the American Musicological Society, a handwritten card signed by attendees, and placemarks for Mr. and Mrs. Kinkeldey.
- Paleographic examples, undated, VII.; Folder 67-71
  Fragments of paleographical examples originally in envelope marked "Vellum leaves, some with neumes".
  - Paleography example number 1, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (15 x 22 cm.) (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Paleography example number 2, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (21 x 15 cm.); Text is "Audite celi que loquar" from the Old Testament of the Bible, Deuteronomy XXXII, 1-43. It is also known as the "Song of Moses". (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Paleography example number 3, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (18 x 10 cm.) with musical neumes; The antiphon text is "Isti sunt duae olivae et duo candelabra lucentia". It is from the New Testament of the Bible, Revelations XI, 4. (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Paleography example number 4, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (4 x 28 cm.) (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Paleography example number 5, undated, 1 manuscript leaf (46 x 11 cm.); The verso is too badly stained to read. (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Compositions by Kinkeldey, 1923, VIII.; Folder 72
  - I'll sing you the song of a flivver, 29 April 1923, 1 manuscript score (3 pages); 35 cm.; "For the N.Y.P.L."--Title page. Words by unknown author; text inserted on separate sheet. (Box 3, Folder 72)
- Transcriptions by Kinkeldey, circa 1900-1940, IX.; Folder 73-146
  Arranged alphabetically by composer, compiler, and collection titles. Works by unidentified composers have been placed last in the series.
  - Ambrose, Saint, Bishop of Milan, d. 397 Veni redemptor gentium. Selections Veni redemptor gentium, undated, 1 leaf of manuscript music; 34 cm.; Pencil manuscript. Two lines of Gregorian chant hymn. (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Attaingnant, Pierre, fl. 1528-1549 Tres breve et familiere introduction. Prelude, no. 1 Tres breve et familiere introduction pour entendre et apprendre par foy mesmes a jouer toutes chansons reduictes en la tablature du Lutz, undated, 3 pages of manuscript music; 35 cm.; Ink manuscript. (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Attaingnant, Pierre, fl. 1528-1549 Selections from five publications by Pierre Attaingnant, undated, 26 pages of manuscript music; 36 cm.; Ink manuscript. Transcribed for keyboard format. (Box 3, Folder 75)